What would you recommend at men over 50
beginning TRT to start working out for
the first time? I guess there are still
a lot of men over 50 when they do have
to start TRT. They've never worked out.
You're recommending resistance training
for.
If you've never worked out in your life,
um then you're likely not even doing the
basic daily activity either that you
need to be doing. So, I usually start uh
by at least having them track their
daily step count and aiming for 8 to
10,000 steps a day. Um, and then adding
in some longer walks of 20 to 30 minutes
at least after dinner would be ideal for
um kind of the blood sugar regulation
benefits. And then if at all possible,
working with a personal trainer at least
a few times before just jumping into
going to the gym regularly so that they
become more comfortable and confident in
what they're doing. Um because so often
I see both young and older guys getting
injured after starting testosterone
because they feel better. They feel like
they want to do more. They feel like
they um have, you know, they have way
more strength they've ever than they
ever had in their life. And then they
get injured and have to take two months
off and they're back even to where they
started with um their endurance. So
you're starting them out just very
lightly with the help of a personal
trainer and then um yeah yeah two to
three days on resistance training I
think is a good place to start um and it
just kind of depends on what access they
have but ideally would work with a
personal trainer so that they can know
what to do instead of just um kind of
guessing and not doing it correctly.
Are they all willing to do the
resistance training?
It depends uh
kind of depends on the population a
little bit um on on who you see there.
There's some differences between our
clinic locations I think on um the type
of patient you see. So like where I work
I have a lot of um guys who do maybe a
significant amount of daily activity
pouring concrete or construction work
farmers um and you don't need to add in
that additional daily activity. and some
of them think they don't need to do any
extra exercise on top of that. Um so
there's some of that discussion of um
determining what needs to be done
outside of their daily work. Um and um
versus the the guy who's sitting at the
desk all day. They they're a little bit
more um open to me telling them what
they should be doing to optimize their
their exercise.